Oh
let's welcome the next speaker Mike
hrabowski Universal react uh talking
about reusing JavaScript's between react
native react web and yeah how to really
write once run everywhere right Mike
hello everyone I also like to welcome
everyone from the livestream I know
there are lots of people watching us so
I hope you can I enjoy this so I'm Mike
and I'm here today to talk to you about
the concept of universal JavaScript and
how thanks to reacts react native we can
build our apps faster and make them more
maintainable before we start a little
bit about myself I'm a CTO at that
company called call stack that IO I've
confounded it last year to help
companies deliver better react native
apps and we do a lot of in the open
source and that's probably why you may
recognize me from what I'm doing with
react native react navigation and a
couple of other repositories we are also
organizing a conference in September
about react native it's called react
native EU if you are interested in
hearing more rare native talks you
should definitely check it out
and so at call stack we have this great
opportunity to iterate on products that
already have existing version of the app
done in the same language usually for
web and that unique opportunity shaped
the way I think about Universal
JavaScript and about the patterns that I
find useful and this talk is going to be
inspired by the findings that we've been
discovering over the past year so let's
get started
first let's start with architecture
overview of a typical app we are usually
building I like to think about those
applications in terms of multi tier
architecture it is a client
client-server architecture in which
presentation layer business layer and
data access layer are kind of physically
separated and the most widespread use of
that architecture is the free tier
architect
with the three layers that I've just
told you in apart from usual advantages
of a module software with well-defined
interfaces that you get such
architecture gives you the unique
opportunity to upgrade or replace each
of these tiers independently during for
instance porting your existing code base
over to a new platform naturally there
is no such an app that can reuse 100% of
the code without compromising on
platform experience and performance
however this is what we are going to
optimize for and this is the best-case
scenario we are optimizing our apps for
so let's take a step back and think how
we used to develop applications in the
past because historically it was never
easy to reuse code it is because we've
been always developing our applications
separately from within independent code
bases we've been kind of creating each
of these applications separately and
that was resulting in features where
implemented in a different way different
sort of bugs being created for each of
these platforms and apart from these
reasons that approach is fundamentally
broken for the following three reasons
first it is expensive to target a new
platform for instance take an example of
Tizen if you are into wearables and
smartwatches you know that Tizen is a
Samsung operating system for
smartwatches and in fact I'm wearing one
right now and by the way this is not
like a paid ad and that operating system
is really smooth really smooth and
somehow feels better than Android wear
in my personal opinion the only problem
that didn't has is it like the apps no
one is developing for it everyone is
targeting Android wear and the system
itself is considered complicated the
second point is that it's slowing us
down as you need more and more
developers more teams to target all the
platforms and develop these features at
the same time and that leads to
inconsistent implementations and
different sort of bugs
then has to fix down the road and
finally there is that platform first
approach where you really is you know
your for example iOS applications first
and it's not only bad for your product
but it's also going to be solve your
users because if they feel abandoned
like for example take take an example of
snapchat that everyone knows that its
iOS first application it used to be an
Android version was lagging behind iOS
like it was slow it was I was unable to
use it and that was the reason I stopped
using it the only reason I installed it
it was that I was in beta Channel I saw
that they fixed it and so if you go with
platform first approach you made peace
of your users in a way that they will
never try your app again and may even
find a replacement so that is important
from the day ones that you don't make
that mistake and personally I think that
one of the biggest problems and
challenges here is that the language
itself is not universal right because
it's tied to a specific platform
environment like with Android we write
Java with objective iOS write
objective-c
these languages have their own runtimes
own semantics build systems and syntax
and it's technically possible to share
code between these platforms you can
write C code and reuse your low-level
modules and this is for example what
Dropbox is doing that however doesn't
scale well and you can't do it for web
so how do we solve it like I wouldn't be
standing here yes the answer could have
been different than JavaScript right one
of the things that I like about it is
that it's widely adapted and present
almost on every machine nowadays you can
get productive with very quickly and it
continues to grow in popularity as more
and more developers are using it one of
the things that is very special about
Jas is something that we call the J's
which which basically which
basically boils down to you know new
frameworks coming out every day and
every day but I believe this is a unique
feature that we have our vibrant
ecosystem keeps looking for improvements
keeps researching and keeps inventing
and that contributes to Rises frameworks
there are aiming to solve the culturing
problem and one of them is react react
native and the entire idea of component
based developed in the component based
interfaces there are two things that I
like about react here first
I like the bahraini by layering react I
can write not only web applications but
now I can write iOS apps I can write
Android apps VR with Windows Phone with
more and more platforms to come we don't
even know what we will be able to do
with react native in the future and the
second thing is that I like how react
encourages us developers to think better
in terms of software developer if you
are like me probably two years ago you
have briefly heard about functional
programming I didn't even do it on my
daily basis I was hoping on the road you
know stateful actions and basically bad
practices now thanks to react my stream
on Twitter is full of immunity immutable
data structure is purity functional
programming and I even started writing
Haskell and other languages so I like
that react makes us better developers
and opens up a lot of possibilities for
us and so one of the concepts that react
popularized was the universal JavaScript
that we are talking about today and
Universal back in a day called
isomorphic stands for the ability of
your code to run on any platform
regardless of the environment this term
is often brought up in a context of
server-side rendering that means our
react components are executed in the
node.js environment where they can
prefetch their data and user receives a
pre rendered HTML output and so that
brings us to another stack which is a
stack of today this is more or less
what's happening right now in variety of
repositories and on Twitter that stack
embraces the idea of universal
JavaScript greatly which is greatly
inspired by the server-side that I've
just told you it eliminates multiple
independent code bases and covers a
single unified source code that is meant
to run on every platform
it builds upon cross-platform libraries
like read rather or react navigation and
uses them everywhere to navigate your
entire web application and your entire
mobile application at first you may feel
like this approach is superior to the
one we have seen before because it fixes
it fixes code duplication because now we
have a single codebase we can write all
the features from the same place and it
eliminates the platform first approach
right because we have the short code
base across all the platforms however at
the same time it unnecessarily
complicates the code base it employs a
lot of workarounds and hacks just to get
things working sometimes it even
compromises on performance just to give
give the promise of your code being
sharable across platforms and a great
example of such not strictly related to
react is PhoneGap and Cordova which if
you are following Twitter recently was
brought up in one of rants about
progressive web apps and all that mobile
battle and so the problem with PhoneGap
is that you can take arbitrary website
and put it as a standalone mobile app
that you can deliver to your clients
that gives you that ability to just drop
in your web site reuse 100% of the code
give to your users but what about
performance right
what about gestures DOM is fundamentally
a different concept and it was never
designed to handle that complex gestures
like pinch or rotation or whatever
multi-touch gestures so these things and
another a lot of other nuances from
mobile platforms that make up a great
user experience we know are just hard to
do that way and that brings me to the
brings me to the fact that I've seen
that we keep missing a big feature here
because we are all coming from web-based
development we keep talking about
server-side rendering and our mental
model gives us the idea of showing
everything like with server-side
rendering our initial thinking is that
we should just have our components
execute on a server
and the output is transferred right to
me Universal JavaScript is different
like it's it's about code portability
than thinking about how can I make my
rap it's run entirely on mobile I should
think what parts of my app are capable
of running on a different platform and
how can I make them to contribute to
overall application that will be done
specifically for that platform and so
that brings me to to the to the
statement that we shouldn't build
Universal applications they are over
engineered over complicated and too much
abstract there is no silver bullet as
far as platform sharing is concerned and
all boiler plates you ever saw that give
you the promise of code reusability are
fundamentally broken at the design level
you can't just take a pre-made solution
and apply it to your different use cases
and reuse your web app to a mobile app
and so instead of building Universal
applications but we should really build
our Universal libraries a new result
universal UI components and so what that
really means to build a universal
libraries it's not for designing our
systems in a way that makes our API and
logic run on every platform regardless
of the of the environment and at first
you may feel that it is the same as
universal JavaScript but the difference
here is significant because instead of
focusing on making your application run
s is on any platform you start thinking
how you can take part of it like an
authentication logic and make it to
contribute to entire iOS for example app
and a web app and that contributes to a
better development cycle within your
product because your developers or you
and your colleagues can focus on solving
specific problems working inside modules
and making sure that the quality of your
app is still at the very high level so
how about universal UI component I
didn't mention react as a dominant
Universal paradigm for no reason right
one of its principles is that component
based model where you don't build a moat
well you don't build an app what you do
is you build small building blocks and
you compose them to create bigger and
bigger and bigger components whereas the
root component is what you call and up
that's how that's how you make it with
react and so building Universal
components means to focus on making
those components platform agnostic which
makes sense and using them to create
platform specific solutions for your
users and that said instead of focusing
on reusing entire navigation prefer
using first cloth rather for the web
user AG router for navigation on mobile
use react navigation but you are free to
reuse the back button right because back
button is a small part of your app
having is reusable is not going to
affect the performance because patches
and containers are very easy to port
across platforms so you shouldn't make
compromises here presentation layers the
initial layer is very complicated and
it's very hard to reach the cross
platforms you may feel that it's easy to
reuse it because we're because Android
and iOS are similar but if you're going
to use react to for example create a VR
app it's going to get complicated and so
in this talk I want to present you the
stack of tomorrow which is a set of
concept that I always apply over my code
bases that I want to make Universal if
you've been following this topic I gave
a very very similar talk
two years ago in Bratislava and I ended
up this thought by saying that there are
three things that has to be fixed in
order to make this a production ready
solution that can be very popular and
recently I was sitting and watching
Twitter and I've realised that we have
made all these things and so now these
the dots pack is ready for the primetime
and I'll explain why in a second of
course I'll share with you the reference
implementation of that after the talk so
please follow me on twitter I'll be
showing the
the lingerer but still keep in mind this
is not a dropping code that you can take
instead analyze the solutions there and
think how many of them applies to your
code so as I said there are three main
aspects of writing Universal code in
this approach that I wanted to highlight
today first of them is setup and our
code setup is very special for two
reasons first we prefer Universal
libraries and user interfaces single
single units of our app over entire
applications that tend to be quite
complex ideally we want to follow that
multi tier architecture that I told that
I showed you at the beginning and keep
iterating on the own parts of our
applications independently second thing
that makes this codebase special is the
concept of utilities I guess like how
many of you have ever probably everyone
created at least one folder called utils
or utilities whose notarizing hand is
probably lying now but okay so the thing
is that I like to think about utilities
as a to be published components and
modules right if your utility is not
ready to be in NPM registry or public on
github because it's tied to your
application logic there's literally an
utility and you should think about how
you structured your application all that
means that the way we are going to work
with our code is going to is going to
involve a lot of independent separate
code bases and repositories which can
get difficult to track and so to solve
these and many other problems we can
organize our code into the multi package
repository that some of you may know as
a mono repo and projects like Babel or
react already utilize that approach to
make the workflow easier and you can see
the example structure on the slide that
has three main folders one of them is
platforms and
but first folder has reached all the
targets that you support now and you are
going to support in the future and there
is the libraries folder where all the
packages that you want to publish in the
future are going to live and the core
where the shared logic is going to be
located and by the way one of the great
things about having libraries that you
are eventually going to publish is the
fact that you start thinking about the
interface about the API and how your
future users are going to use it which
makes you to think twice before you
create a file create another abstraction
which contributes the better codebase
and so if you want to automate the
process of working with your codebase
you are free to use lerna a tool that
was designed specifically for empowering
that kind of workflow it has a bunch of
comments for example you can learn a
bootstrap to automatically link all the
repositories with each other which makes
this process really easy this setup
really easy to work and so very
important part of this entire workflow
is webpack it's been it's been quite
it's in quite last-minute with web pack
because we've been working on bringing
web packs to react natives for quite a
while and I was working on that with
Satya you may know him Satya won 6-4
he's also working a vertical stack and
by the way if he is watching live stream
we can now all say happy birthday
because his birthday are today yeah so
so we have we've been working on that
together for quite a while and hopeful
like fortunately we made it and like
what was the buzz all about so to
compose universal modules and user
interfaces together you need a universal
bundler like web pack and we know that
web pack is a powerful and extensible
library that has a lot of features
including first-class support for some
links and so the entire idea of bundling
system like web pack is to take your
application code starting from an entry
point and serve a bundle so if you are
working with rig natives this is exactly
what the react native package Ares
the only difference is that we wanted to
use a single build pipeline for all the
targets so that we can make it Universal
and reuse our conflicts and so thanks to
whole react native can now benefit from
that and we can use webpack quite easily
with react native to deliver pretty much
everything that we can with web and the
last part and the last part of our setup
which is very important this bubble as I
mentioned before javascript is a wildly
adapt language now that's only because
it's been around for a while the problem
is that with every browser out there you
never know what's the target versions of
supported and for example iOS 10 and iOS
9 and iOS 8 shipped with Safari that has
a different subset of features and that
the like they ship with JavaScript core
which is running your react native
engine or a native code and that Safari
supports a different subset of features
for example in iOS than it suffers the
full es2015 spec whereas on iOS 9 it
only supports a sub spec and so bubble
is a grateful for that because it allows
us to transpile our code to support any
target that we that we that we want to
that we want to use it and run our
application on and so the translation is
the process of taking our J's code
applying set of transforms and returning
something that can run on a react native
and so there are a bunch of
optimizations that we can do thanks to
bubble and thanks to using it here and
we have another targets we can reuse our
extensions there are two very
interesting concepts that you can that
you can do for example with react native
one of the performance improvements is
that you can inline all the platform
calls you probably have been using
platform module for selectively
rendering some stuff in react native so
these codes are inline and during the
compile time so now that we have a
foundation for showing our code that's
setup let's take a look at common
techniques for doing so so the most
important and the
basic approach is to use platform
extensions such as such as the ones that
are allowed by RIT native packager this
is crucial for creating cross-platform
experience it allows people to override
default implementations by creating
platform specific files the idea is that
having an arbitrary file like in this
case index dot JSP SJS that will be
specifically loaded on iOS - for example
override the default tab bar this works
out of the box in react native and with
web 5 you can make it with resolve that
extensions which again brings us to the
point at web bug is a perfect solution
for universally bundling our
applications and as far as as far as
presentation layer goes I mentioned that
it's it's kind of complex and it
requires us to think deeper before we
start sharing things one of the things
that is important is to understand the
different levels of sharing there are
two of them and one is the local level
the local level is when you for example
sure your clients eyes react on server
side or when you share your iOS we've
Android you stick to the single
environment you're just sharing code
between different different devices
right and this is easy this is easy
because for iOS and Android you can
reuse the entire UI I'm not talking
about user experience now like
performance wise no differences here you
can just use it however at platform
level things we have quite complicated
because you have to understand that not
necessarily everything that you know
from web or react native or mobile can
be run at the same time on different
platforms so the answer to that problem
is that we should use primitives over
press on specific controls and so the
problem is that if you want to really
share your user interface component you
don't want to implement it enzymes for
end platform for everyone's to created
one for all the platforms and that's
what primitives are for to better
illustrate us consider this example
where I'm creating a component
that's essentially just a wrapper right
this component what is doing is wrapping
my children with a div tag and applying
some sort of styling ABC problem is I'm
using a host component I'm using Dom DS
component which is entirely breaking the
idea of code sharing right there is no
Dom related thing here it's just that I
used the attack it's no longer going to
run on a mobile and so the idea is to
use a generic wrapper kind of like a
view that can adapt its behavior based
on the platform and make it easy to
build generic environment agnostic unit
of interface and there are various
implementations and takes at this
problem including recently open source 3
XP by Microsoft that I encourage you to
check and react native web which is the
parallel implementation of react native
meant to run on web and react primitives
that I'm using in this example so
sometimes when we all we need is just a
simple wrapper like in this case using
the entire library it's probably not
efficient and you can what you can do is
you can use the file extensions solution
that we seen before so that's all about
presentation layer and as far as sharing
of layers goes there is also business
layer and middle layer is quite easy to
share because we can take advantage of
javascript javascript is running on
mobile in our web with no differences so
we can quite easily share the code and
to better illustrate the approaches let
me let me tell you two examples that I
highlighted here behind below the
heading one of them is the async storage
module that we made at call stack which
takes the async storage from react
native and local search from web e and
integrates both implementations into a
single library it abstracts away the
differences for you errors and all the
other api's which means that you can use
it regardless of the platform and the
second round is react navigation where
all you have to do is where is
recognition well what we do is we take a
single codebase and we ship the web
version that contains the logic and we
ship the mobile version
that contains also tabview drawer and
stack which are mobile specific user
interfaces as far as sharing your
business logic goes you don't have to
use red X but I'm mentioning it here
because I like to think of red acts as a
protocol for sharing business logic it
externalizes your state it moves your
state away from react which makes it
easy to switch the Dom layer to
something entirely different not only
you can switch from web to mobile but
also you can switch from react to view
GIS or
entirely different frame or given
vanilla J as in electron up depending on
what you are targeting and another thing
that I like about radix is its
simplicity and extensibility because it
has the concept of middle worst and so
if I have if I have an async action as
in this case and what to send user
details I want to use a fetch library on
web and mobile but for example from
terminal I want to use the command line
to fetch a certain resource for me so
having the ability to inject context to
your actions like in this case allows
you to change the dependencies on per
environment basis and even if you don't
need it now all you have to do it also
helps you with testing so the takeaway
for today is that code mobility is
important not only you should be able to
read off any part of your code and
replace it with another one in today's
world you should also be able to target
new environments and platforms without
rewriting things from scratch all over
again there is no universal pattern or
paradigm to that problem
our cure bases are different clients
have different ideas and most
importantly technologies change so I
encourage you to innovate and keep
looking for that optimal solution thank
you
[Applause]